<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dovetail.prx.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://dovetail.prx.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-12-16T14:38:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dovetail.prx.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dovetail from PRX</title><subtitle>Podcast distribution &amp; Privacy forward ad tech platform
</subtitle><author><name>PRX</name><email>dovetail@prx.org</email></author><entry><title type="html">Dovetail Glossary</title><link href="https://dovetail.prx.org/2022/12/02/dovetail-glossary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dovetail Glossary" /><published>2022-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dovetail.prx.org/2022/12/02/dovetail-glossary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dovetail.prx.org/2022/12/02/dovetail-glossary"><![CDATA[<h2 id="podcast-metrics">Podcast Metrics</h2>

<p><strong>Download:</strong> A podcast episode download. As defined by the <a href="https://iabtechlab.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/PodcastMeasurement_v2.1.pdf">IAB 2.1 Podcast Measurement guidelines</a>, a listener must download enough of the episode creative file for 1-minute of audio to be counted.</p>

<p><strong>Impression:</strong> A podcast ad impression. Also defined in the <a href="https://iabtechlab.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/PodcastMeasurement_v2.1.pdf">IAB 2.1 Podcast Measurement guidelines</a>, the listener must have downloaded all of the bytes in the episode creative file where the ad can be heard to be counted.
<em>Also see: “Actual”</em></p>

<h2 id="podcast-layouts">Podcast Layouts</h2>

<p><strong>Placements:</strong> The configured layouts of a podcast’s audio segments. Each is made up of a list of Zones. If there are no placements configured for an audio template, vanilla/ad-free audio will be served.
Example: [Preroll1 Preroll2 Original1 Midroll Original2 Postroll]</p>

<p><strong>Zone:</strong> A single audio segment within an episode, including both original and ad segments.
<em>Example: House Preroll 2</em></p>

<p><strong>Section:</strong> A grouping of consecutive ad Zones into a single block. May also distinguish between “paid” and “house” ads.
<em>Example: Preroll (containing both Preroll1 and Preroll2)</em></p>

<h2 id="ad-serving">Ad Serving</h2>

<p><strong>Campaign:</strong> Represents an Inventory Order (IO) for a single advertiser. It can contain many Flights.</p>

<p><strong>Flight:</strong> One or more creatives plus a set of targeting information to serve with a podcast. Configured with Zones, a date-range, and an Impression goal.
Ads are fulfilled by reserving Allocations against future Inventory.</p>

<p><strong>Creative:</strong> Refers to the audio file (MP3, WAV, FLAC) or VAST URL containing the ad content.</p>

<p><strong>VAST:</strong> An acronym that stands for Video Ad Serving Template. VAST is a way for multiple ad servers to communicate and serve ads, replacing individual ad audio files for a campaign with a VAST URL.</p>

<p><strong>Forecast:</strong> The daily forecasted Downloads we expect a podcast to receive in the future. May also be broken out by Episode, Country, State, Keywords, etc.</p>

<p><strong>Inventory:</strong> The daily number of Impressions available for ad Zones to be sold into in the future. (Equal to the Forecast multiplied by the ad Placements - original segment Zones do not get Inventory).</p>

<p><strong>Allocations:</strong> The daily Inventory counts reserved by a Flight. May include additional targeting info such as Episode, Country, State, Keywords, etc.</p>

<p><strong>Availability:</strong> The amount of unreserved Inventory left in the system (subtract the Allocations for whatever days/targeting you’re looking at).</p>

<p><strong>Actuals:</strong> The number of real Impressions a flight has already received.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ryan Cavis</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Commonly used podcasting terms and definitions used throughout Dovetail from PRX]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://dovetail.prx.org/assets/img/hero-features.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://dovetail.prx.org/assets/img/hero-features.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Dovetail from PRX?</title><link href="https://dovetail.prx.org/2022/10/07/what-is-dovetail-from-prx" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Dovetail from PRX?" /><published>2022-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dovetail.prx.org/2022/10/07/what-is-dovetail-from-prx</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dovetail.prx.org/2022/10/07/what-is-dovetail-from-prx"><![CDATA[<p><em>Note: This article was originally posted on <a href="https://medium.com/prxofficial/what-is-dovetail-from-prx-e2d1b7f79c3">PRX’s company blog</a>.</em></p>

<p>PRX is one of the largest podcast distributors — both in terms of the number of shows and downloads per month of each show — in the world. To ensure the reliable delivery of hundreds of thousands of podcast impressions daily, we count on our podcast publishing platform, Dovetail from PRX.</p>

<p><a href="/">Dovetail from PRX</a> is a suite of applications for podcast post-production built on the values and trust of public media. In its everyday context, a dovetail is “a joint formed by one or more tapered projections (tenons) on one piece which interlocks with corresponding notches or recesses (mortises) in another.”</p>

<p>It looks like this:</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-1-200-4627c2b70.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-1-323-4627c2b70.webp 323w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-1-200-31d0c317b.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-1-323-31d0c317b.png 323w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-1-323-31d0c317b.png" alt="dovetail joint in woodworking" width="323" height="255" /></picture>

<p>In our context, Dovetail refers to the platform’s power to seamlessly stitch together pieces of produced audio, a central feature of post-production needs.</p>

<h2 id="what-does-dovetail-from-prx-do">What does Dovetail from PRX do?</h2>

<p>Dovetail gives producers a smooth podcast publishing experience and the framework to grow, monetize, and sustain their podcast business in today’s open podcast ecosystem. From a birds-eye view, Dovetail does three main things: podcast distribution, data collection, and ad inventory management.</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body2-200-bc0641b86.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body2-400-bc0641b86.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body2-600-bc0641b86.webp 600w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body2-200-c8729fbd9.jpeg 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body2-400-c8729fbd9.jpeg 400w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body2-600-c8729fbd9.jpeg 600w" type="image/jpeg" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dt-body2-600-c8729fbd9.jpeg" alt="screenshot of Dovetail episode form" width="600" height="400" /></picture>

<h2 id="podcast-distribution-made-easy">Podcast distribution made easy</h2>

<p>We’ve designed the content management and podcast feed hosting features to empower producers with the flexibility and support they need to publish, manage, and easily update their podcasts across all podcast platforms.</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-3-200-7cbb99ee9.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-3-400-7cbb99ee9.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-3-720-7cbb99ee9.webp 720w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-3-200-74a8dcfa0.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-3-400-74a8dcfa0.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-3-720-74a8dcfa0.png 720w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-3-720-74a8dcfa0.png" alt="GBH, KCRW, KERA, WAMU are all public media stations on Dovetail" width="720" height="253" /></picture>

<p>Dovetail hosts more than 260 podcasts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Major public media organizations and stations trust PRX’s platform to publish their podcasts, such as PBS, GBH, KERA, WAMU, WUNC, KCRW, KUOW, and WPLN.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Many of the radio programs that PRX brings to the airwaves are also some of the biggest podcasts, relying on our podcast distribution technology: “Snap Judgment,” “The Moth Radio Hour,” “Reveal,” “Latino USA,” and more. You may also be familiar with podcasts part of Radiotopia from PRX, like “Ear Hustle,” “Song Exploder,” “The Stoop,” “Radio Diaries,” “The Heart,” and “The Kitchen Sisters Present.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Remarkable audio producers beyond public media — including indie creators and mission-oriented creators — also rely on PRX’s distribution technology: TED, the Smithsonian, The Boston Globe, Religion of Sports, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Project Brazen, and many more.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-4-200-c5e40bc2e.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-4-400-c5e40bc2e.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-4-600-c5e40bc2e.webp 600w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-4-200-b15f8df6b.jpeg 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-4-400-b15f8df6b.jpeg 400w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-4-600-b15f8df6b.jpeg 600w" type="image/jpeg" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-4-600-b15f8df6b.jpeg" alt="screenshot of metrics by media market in Dovetail" width="600" height="400" /></picture>

<h2 id="data-that-leads-to-strategic-decisions">Data that leads to strategic decisions</h2>

<p>Through Dovetail’s near real-time data and inventory forecasting features, producers have the information they need to make decisions about their audiences and revenue opportunities.</p>

<p>With the metrics Dovetail provides, producers will understand their podcasts’ performance downloads by applications and devices and their audience size by country, state, or metro. This data is available to keep within our portal or export to your own systems.</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-5-200-9c588b9a4.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-5-400-9c588b9a4.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-5-600-9c588b9a4.webp 600w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-5-200-ba345e9ca.jpeg 200w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-5-400-ba345e9ca.jpeg 400w, /assets/generated/img/dt-body-5-600-ba345e9ca.jpeg 600w" type="image/jpeg" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dt-body-5-600-ba345e9ca.jpeg" alt="screenshot of searching for availability in Dovetail" width="600" height="400" /></picture>

<h2 id="harness-the-full-potential-of-monetization">Harness the full potential of monetization</h2>

<p>Dovetail gives producers the confidence to sell inventory and the assurance of reaching their impressions. The impression forecast feature predicts an episode’s performance based on the show’s historical drop data. With Dovetail, sales teams can easily understand a podcast’s availability and sell-through rate at any given time in the future — ensuring all inventory is accounted for and used.</p>

<p>Producers save time, costs, and resources while also maximizing profits by hosting their podcasts on Dovetail. Our dynamic ad insertion technology easily attaches sponsorship messages into produced audio to create what listeners experience as a final, polished episode. Gone are the days of only selling ad inventory on upcoming episodes; with Dovetail’s dynamic ad insertion, timely sponsorship messages can be added to every episode in a portfolio and tailored to a specific audience.</p>

<h2 id="scale-your-podcast-without-compromising-listeners-privacy">Scale your podcast without compromising listeners’ privacy</h2>

<p>Privacy is one of the platform’s defining characteristics. Trust is a two-way street, and public media’s ability to thrive depends on our listeners’ trust in us. Sharing and misusing personal data, like IP addresses, and tracking people’s internet activity without permission violates that trust.</p>

<p>In another post, we’ll go into all the technical details of how Dovetail is at the forefront of security. Still, we’ll leave you with this: privacy regulations are strengthening, not weakening. Content creators need to be ready for how that can impact their ad sales and revenue.</p>

<p>If you already publish podcasts or are exploring podcasting, we hope you will consider Dovetail for your podcast distribution needs.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brandon Hundt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A privacy-first suite of applications for all your podcasting needs.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://dovetail.prx.org/assets/img/hero-stations.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://dovetail.prx.org/assets/img/hero-stations.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing Inventory Management in Dovetail from PRX</title><link href="https://dovetail.prx.org/2022/07/21/introducing-dovetail-as-product" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Inventory Management in Dovetail from PRX" /><published>2022-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dovetail.prx.org/2022/07/21/introducing-dovetail-as-product</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dovetail.prx.org/2022/07/21/introducing-dovetail-as-product"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past year, PRX carefully migrated our podcasts to our latest version of Dovetail - that now includes end to end ad inventory management.</p>

<p>Our Advertising Operations (Ad-Ops) team is now able to manage advertising campaigns from front to end in one system, including near real-time forecasts and availability broken down by Geo-targets available as the inventory order (IO) is being inserted.</p>

<p>Dovetail is a podcasting post-production suite of applications that excels in delivering dynamically inserted content, including the original audio files and ad creatives to your intended audience in a privacy conscious way.</p>

<h2 id="why-we-added-inventory-management-into-dovetail">Why we added inventory management into Dovetail</h2>
<p>For many years at PRX, we’ve been using dynamic ad insertion to ensure that ads were properly inserted into podcasts. As shows were published into PRX Publish, our APIs connected to a third party ad service (Kevel) and a script we wrote “Dovetail” rearranged the mp3 files into the desired order.</p>

<p>Building your own ad server is really hard. So by using Kevel we could lean on really good technology out of the box. As our CTO, Andrew Kuklewicz, points out in <a href="https://soundsprofitable.com/article/kevel">an interview</a> with <em>Sounds Profitable</em> host Bryan Barletta, the initial integration wasn’t very difficult and at the time made sense.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CkZfvubCfSE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>However, after hundreds of millions, maybe billions, of ad impressions later, we learned we needed to be more efficient in our process. We really didn’t have a ton of visibility into the full inventory picture and it was difficult to forecast potential availability.</p>

<p>PRX’s Ad-Ops team did some serious spreadsheet magic to help manage the inventory. But a very large volume of inventory caused managing the sheets a challenge to manage. Quickly, the spreadsheet became so complex that it hit the limit of cells available in Google Sheets - something I wasn’t aware was realistically possible.</p>

<p>We were not certain if this was something to celebrate or if it was a cry for help. Certainly, the spreadsheet skills of our scrappy Ad-Ops team is undeniable and worthy of celebration - as they have worked tirelessly to successfully serve millions of ads in our podcasts in a month.</p>

<p>But there had to be a better way, a more efficient way that doesn’t rely on Google Sheets to track our ad inventory.</p>

<p>Consider forecasting. This well built spreadsheet was unable to keep up with changes and segments that would allow us to forecast future downloads without huge confidence buffers.</p>

<p>In other words, we have been leaving money on the table - money that the bulk of, goes back into the hands of our independent producers to create fine podcasts.</p>

<p>At PRX, we embrace the principles of design thinking and user centric design in building out our tech products. One of the central tenets of design thinking is fully understanding the needs of a single user and designing a product that fits their needs. In our case our user is the PRX Ad-Ops team.</p>

<p>If we correctly assume that the needs of the PRX Ad-Ops team are the same needs of other Ad-Ops teams in podcasting, then we have a product that would be helpful to independent podcasters across the industry.</p>

<p>So we, the PRX tech team, after hearing the cries of our Ad-Ops team started to work hand in hand with our Ad-Ops teams to consider how we could simplify the process of ad inventory management by solving for two goals, as outlined above:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Developing a better forecast of podcast performance</li>
  <li>Retiring the Google Spreadsheet</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="forecasting">Forecasting</h2>
<p>To more accurately forecast, we started by adding a Production calendar feature into our Dovetail Publish CMS and encouraging producers to add drafts of when they know future episodes will drop - even if its only a date in the future.</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/1-production-calendar-200-96d7022f9.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/1-production-calendar-400-96d7022f9.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/1-production-calendar-800-96d7022f9.webp 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/1-production-calendar-1196-96d7022f9.webp 1196w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/1-production-calendar-200-b46d94dce.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/1-production-calendar-400-b46d94dce.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/1-production-calendar-800-b46d94dce.png 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/1-production-calendar-1196-b46d94dce.png 1196w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/1-production-calendar-800-b46d94dce.png" alt="screenshot of the production calendar in Dovetail" width="1196" height="665" /></picture>

<p>In addition, we also have a lot of IAB compliant data on how well our podcasts have performed historically. This data is made available in our Dovetail Metrics platform.</p>

<p><strong><em>Related: <a href="https://medium.com/prxofficial/five-features-of-prx-metrics-we-want-to-you-to-know-about-f3aceb15b47b">Here are five features in Metrics we want you to know about</a></em></strong></p>

<p>Knowing when episodes will drop and how they’ve performed historically allows us to predict how well we think a podcast is going to perform with some reliability using the statistical programming language R.</p>

<p>Here’s an example of one of the R generated forecasts:</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-200-65105894b.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-400-65105894b.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-800-65105894b.webp 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-1200-65105894b.webp 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-1365-65105894b.webp 1365w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-200-b1bcbf0b6.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-400-b1bcbf0b6.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-800-b1bcbf0b6.png 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-1200-b1bcbf0b6.png 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-1365-b1bcbf0b6.png 1365w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/2-forecast-800-b1bcbf0b6.png" alt="screenshot of a forecast in Dovetail" width="1365" height="655" /></picture>

<p>There are variables to accuracy, like how new a show is, or how often a show publishes - for example we’ve found that podcasts that drop daily are much easier to predict. This will give our Ad-Ops team more confidence on how aggressively a show can be sold.</p>

<p>Our forecasts are also flexible enough to handle some more advanced targeting based on IAB 2.0 compliant and privacy focused segmented audience data, like location.</p>

<h2 id="inventory-order-input">Inventory Order Input</h2>
<p>Early in the process of building out inventory management capabilities we identified benchmarks for shows by the complexity of their advertising needs. We knew we couldn’t retire the aforementioned Inventory spreadsheets until we moved all of our podcasts over to the new system, helping us to identify the features we absolutely needed to have vs those we didn’t right away.</p>

<p>The first thing we identified is that we needed to ensure that our Ad-Ops team had a simple and easy to use application in which they can quickly add new IOs and segment them as they need.</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-200-088c01dcb.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-400-088c01dcb.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-800-088c01dcb.webp 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-1200-088c01dcb.webp 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-1600-088c01dcb.webp 1600w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-200-4a1d5ef54.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-400-4a1d5ef54.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-800-4a1d5ef54.png 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-1200-4a1d5ef54.png 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-1600-4a1d5ef54.png 1600w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/3-flight-form-800-4a1d5ef54.png" alt="screenshot of campaign and flight entry in Dovetail" width="1674" height="810" /></picture>

<p>What we think is the best feature of the campaign insertion form is the near real time forecasts available as you target ad zones within the podcast.</p>

<p>We also created a dashboard that allows campaign managers to quickly view and filter campaigns and flights to more easily manage and track the orders that have already been added.</p>

<h2 id="availability-at-a-glance">Availability at a Glance</h2>
<p>PRX has a strong partnership with Market Enginuity for our podcast ad sales. One critical element of replacing the inventory spreadsheets was to create a simple view for Account Executives to quickly look up availability.</p>

<p>Therefore, we’ve built a dashboard that does just that. Look up availability:</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-200-a36665b18.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-400-a36665b18.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-800-a36665b18.webp 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-1200-a36665b18.webp 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-1600-a36665b18.webp 1600w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-200-7fdc6376a.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-400-7fdc6376a.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-800-7fdc6376a.png 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-1200-7fdc6376a.png 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-1600-7fdc6376a.png 1600w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/4-avails-search-800-7fdc6376a.png" alt="screenshot of availability search in Dovetail" width="1669" height="768" /></picture>

<h2 id="our-commitment-to-listener-privacy">Our Commitment to Listener Privacy</h2>
<p>PRX is strongly committed to listener privacy. We are IAB 2.0 compliant, we only store a quartile of an IP address and we don’t track what you listen to – only that someone downloaded a podcast.</p>

<p>PRX believes that the future of digital ads is in contextual advertising; where advertisers buy ads against content, not listeners. This will help keep more money in the pockets of our producers - allowing them to create more engaging content that you want to listen to.</p>

<p>Within Dovetail, we are continuing to improve our platform to increase content tagging capabilities and discoverability.</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-200-e0f90e613.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-400-e0f90e613.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-800-e0f90e613.webp 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-1200-e0f90e613.webp 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-1600-e0f90e613.webp 1600w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-200-96898a1f4.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-400-96898a1f4.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-800-96898a1f4.png 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-1200-96898a1f4.png 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-1600-96898a1f4.png 1600w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/6-category-blocks-800-96898a1f4.png" alt="screenshot of Brand Safety category selection in Dovetail" width="1671" height="749" /></picture>

<h2 id="privacy-forward-programmatic-advertising">Privacy-forward Programmatic Advertising</h2>
<p>While we believe in the future of contextual advertising, there are use cases in which it makes sense to carefully use programmatic advertising exchanges to help our producers. For example, we have a large show with a large international audience, and programmatic is a way to help fill availability inventory.</p>

<p>We also have a lot of small shows or new shows that may be considered too small to sell ads into directly. In this case, programmatic ads can really help a show get off the ground floor.</p>

<p>VAST tags are becoming a standard in podcasting to request programmatic ads. We’ve worked with AdsWhizz to create a way to use VAST, while protecting listener privacy. This may mean that we won’t have access to all of the exchanges that exist, or have the ability to target listeners in all the ways possible, and that is fine by us. We want to vet and understand the sources for the ads our listeners receive.</p>

<p>Fortunately, our partners at Market Enginuity have created a privacy forward programmatic ad exchange that we can pull ads from to help producers.</p>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-200-dc6f5422d.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-400-dc6f5422d.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-800-dc6f5422d.webp 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-1200-dc6f5422d.webp 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-1600-dc6f5422d.webp 1600w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-200-78c163ab9.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-400-78c163ab9.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-800-78c163ab9.png 800w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-1200-78c163ab9.png 1200w, /assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-1600-78c163ab9.png 1600w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/dovetail/5-vast-800-78c163ab9.png" alt="screenshot of a VAST creative in Dovetail" width="1688" height="580" /></picture>

<h2 id="self-service-dovetail">Self-Service Dovetail</h2>
<p>We made a bet that our Ad-Ops team handles the same use cases that Ad-Ops teams across podcasting and outside of PRX come across on a near daily basis. This is a professional tool for professionals that respect user privacy and helps grow producer revenue. This may be the tool you need to grow your shows. If so, feel free to reach out us.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brandon Hundt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understand your inventory with best in class inventory management.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://dovetail.prx.org/assets/img/homepage-hero.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://dovetail.prx.org/assets/img/homepage-hero.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Five features of PRX Metrics we want you to know about</title><link href="https://dovetail.prx.org/2019/09/06/five-features-of-prx-metrics-we-want-to-you-to-know-about" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five features of PRX Metrics we want you to know about" /><published>2019-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dovetail.prx.org/2019/09/06/five-features-of-prx-metrics-we-want-to-you-to-know-about</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dovetail.prx.org/2019/09/06/five-features-of-prx-metrics-we-want-to-you-to-know-about"><![CDATA[<p><em>Note: This article was originally posted on <a href="https://medium.com/prxofficial/five-features-of-prx-metrics-we-want-to-you-to-know-about-f3aceb15b47b">PRX’s company blog</a>.</em></p>

<p>PRX’s <a href="https://www.prx.org/services/publishing-platform">publishing platform</a> is at the heart of our mission to serve audio creators. It allows producers to easily add new content and distribute it across an ever increasing list of listening apps and technologies (like smart speakers.)</p>

<p>In the past year, we’ve been working hard to further deliver on this mission by adding new features to Metrics, our in-house data platform that allows producers to see the impact of and audience for their stories. It shows all the unique downloads for podcast audio, from every platform and player, so that producers can realize their vision, take measurable risks, and make more meaningful media.</p>

<p>The tech team is proud of our recent work because of the value Metrics brings to producers. Here’s what Sandi Barr, PRX Senior Software Engineer and Metrics Champion™ says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <em>It’s so important for podcasters to have access to and be able to make the most out of their data. The podcasts we carry on PRX are owned and managed by the users — independent producers, media companies, and public radio stations. We’re so proud that we can offer them a platform along with our guidance and leadership in the industry to help them better understand and make use of their data to grow their reach.</em>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="how-metrics-works">How Metrics Works:</h2>

<p>The glue of the PRX publishing platform is <a rel="noopener" href="/prxofficial/on-dovetail-618153c4d67e">Dovetail</a>, an application that seamlessly inserts sponsorship messaging with podcast episodes uploaded into our content management system, Publish. Also inserted into each episode by Dovetail is a pixel tracker that counts when an episode is streamed or downloaded.</p>

<p>Dovetail then provides the data in its API to Metrics, which displays it in a frontend built using Angular.</p>

<p>Note: PRX strongly believes in user privacy.<strong> </strong>All the pixel tracker collects are a count of the download, a timestamp, the user-agent reported from the app itself, and a portion of the IP address to report location.<strong> None of this can directly tie back to a single listener, meaning the listener is fully anonymous to our publishing platform.</strong> <strong>All we know is that somebody listened, not who.</strong> Furthermore, we do not collect any information on what other podcasts people may be listening to. What they listen to is their business, not ours.</p>

<p>I’d like to highlight 5 features of Metrics that empower creators.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="1-near-real-time-data-updates-and-flexible-time-selection">1) Near real time data updates and flexible time selection</h2>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-1-200-19febdfa2.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-1-400-19febdfa2.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-1-720-19febdfa2.webp 720w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-1-200-8a4ea7ec2.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-1-400-8a4ea7ec2.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-1-720-8a4ea7ec2.png 720w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-1-720-8a4ea7ec2.png" alt="screenshot of PRX Metrics date selection" width="720" height="374" /></picture>

<p>Our producers can begin to track episode performance as soon as they publish an episode. Metrics has the latest data within minutes of a new listen being recorded by Dovetail, allowing producers to receive live updates of traffic on an episode.</p>

<p>Users can measure episode performance in custom time ranges based on the unique cadence of each show (daily, weekly, seasonality).</p>

<h2 id="2-drop-day-charts">2) Drop day charts</h2>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-200-78c55a2c2.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-400-78c55a2c2.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-720-78c55a2c2.webp 720w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-200-6f536a087.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-400-6f536a087.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-720-6f536a087.png 720w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-720-6f536a087.png" alt="screenshot of PRX Metrics drop day charts" width="720" height="247" /></picture>

<p>Leveraging real time data, we built a Drop Day chart to help creators see for themselves how episodes compared to one another in the hours and days following an episode drop. This allows producers to better understand the timing of releasing podcast episodes.</p>

<p>For example, if a producer of a weekly podcast releases a podcast a few hours later than normal (or even a day later,) they can directly see the impact that the publishing delay may have on traffic, positive or negative.</p>

<h2 id="3-easily-switch-between-your-shows">3) Easily switch between your shows</h2>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-3-200-34ef858d5.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-3-400-34ef858d5.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-3-720-34ef858d5.webp 720w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-3-200-a94042fd7.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-3-400-a94042fd7.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-3-720-a94042fd7.png 720w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-3-720-a94042fd7.png" alt="show switcher" width="720" height="180" /></picture>

<p>Many of the creators that use our publishing platform produce multiple podcasts, so we’ve provided easy ways to navigate between them.</p>

<h2 id="4-aggregated-show-downloads-you-can-see-a-single-episode-or-compare-releases">4) Aggregated show downloads. You can see a single episode, or compare releases.</h2>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-4-200-56b09cb18.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-4-400-56b09cb18.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-4-720-56b09cb18.webp 720w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-4-200-c1eb8ea6a.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-4-400-c1eb8ea6a.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-4-720-c1eb8ea6a.png 720w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-4-720-c1eb8ea6a.png" alt="screenshot of PRX Metrics episode list" width="720" height="339" /></picture>

<p>To this point, we’ve focused a lot on tracking individual episodes, but creators can also check data across a series of episode releases and export it to CSV or Google Sheets. Data is also rolled up to easily see how your selected range compares to the all-time stats for a show.</p>

<h2 id="5-information-about-where-listeners-are-located-and-the-apps-they-use-to-hear-your-show">5) Information about where listeners are located, and the apps they use to hear your show</h2>

<picture><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-200-78c55a2c2.webp 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-400-78c55a2c2.webp 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-720-78c55a2c2.webp 720w" type="image/webp" /><source sizes="(max-width: 480px) calc(100vw - 16px), (max-width: 768) 80vw, 1200px" srcset="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-200-6f536a087.png 200w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-400-6f536a087.png 400w, /assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-720-6f536a087.png 720w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/generated/img/metrics-body-2-720-6f536a087.png" alt="screenshot of PRX Metrics apps performance list" width="720" height="247" /></picture>

<p>Previously, I mentioned how Dovetail’s pixel tracker collects some non-personally identifiable data. We report this to producers using Metrics through maps, charts and tables. Producers can look up listenership by country or metro area (DSM), as well as by device and the podcast app used — assuming the podcast app provides a user-agent we can use to track. This gives producers useful information to make marketing decisions regarding ad spend and promotion opportunities.</p>

<hr />

<p>To conclude, many folks played a part in the development of Metrics, but I’d like to single out three for a shout out: the aforementioned Sandi Barr, Technical Lead Ryan Cavis, and Director of Design Chris Kalafarski. 🌮 Tacos all around.</p>]]></content><author><name>Brandon Hundt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[PRX’s Metrics platform empowers audio producers with download and audience data]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://dovetail.prx.org/assets/img/metrics-post-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://dovetail.prx.org/assets/img/metrics-post-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>